Here's what you need to know about the Claudine Gay plagiarism scandal.
It's bullshit. Let me explain.
Christopher Ruffo, he's the guy that started the critical race theory panic.
This is his thing.
So he dropped this Twitter thread in which he claimed to prove that Claudine Gay had plagiarized her thesis
while she was studying for a PhD at Harvard.
This supposed bombshell hinges on two claims.
First is that Claudine Gay plagiarized her thesis advisor.
Here's the thing.
Your thesis advisor is your co-author, not some source you found on the internet.
Plagiarism is passing off someone else's work as your own work.
A thesis advisor knows the difference between their own work and their students' work.
That's kind of their job.
And there's inevitably a lot of overlap between the professor's work and the student's work.
That's the nature of the advisor-advisee relationship.
Claudine Gay's thesis advisor, Gary King, knew full well which parts of Claudine Gay's thesis
were derived from his work.
There is no plausible way that Claudine Gay tried to pass off her thesis advisor's work as her own.
Like, it's just stupid.
Now if you point this out to somebody who's already made up their mind that Claudine Gay is a plagiarist,
they will immediately pivot to the second claim, which I'll get to in just a second.
But first, consider the pivot.
Because it gives away the whole game.
When you point out how ridiculous it is to claim that Claudine Gay plagiarized her thesis advisor
on her thesis, I haven't seen anybody try to defend that claim.
They just pivot to the other one.
What does that tell you?
They didn't believe the first claim.
They don't believe the second one either.
That's not the point.
The point is to stack up as many bullshit claims as they can get away with.
Because most people haven't done grad-level writing.
They don't have the context to understand the stupidity of the claim.
Anyway, the second claim is also from the thesis.
Claudine Gay cites some sources to describe the methods that they use as context for her own work.
In the course of doing that, she repeats some of the original source verbiage, close to word-for-word.
And of course, Rufo puts the two pieces of text side by side.
And says, look, she didn't cite her source!
The fact that there is a citation at the beginning of the paragraph notwithstanding.
If you know anybody that's done academic writing, ask them about writing the methods section.
That's where you describe the technical details of the research that you did.
Here's the thing about highly technical writing.
You're trying to describe a set of very specific concepts.
A lot of times using terminology that nobody outside your field understands.
The number of ways that you can phrase a piece of technical writing and have it still make sense and be accurate is generally pretty small.
One of the lines that Rufo highlighted was using 1987 survey data, which is a technical description of a source of data that was used to do some analysis.
And as part of Rufo's little op, he pointed out that the original text said using 1987 national sample survey data.
And says, oh, look, these are basically the same.
Which is true, but think about this for a second.
How many ways can you rephrase that?
The study used survey data from 1987.
You can't change 1987, right?
Because then it wouldn't be accurate.
It was survey data, so what are you going to change it to something else?
It doesn't work because it's specific.
And it's important to convey the specifics in your academic writing.
Besides, it's the methods section of the paper, which is not the part that is what you're actually trying to contribute with your research.
That comes in the results and conclusions, and arguably also the introduction, not in the methods.
The point of the methods is to give a high-level overview of how you got the results you did.
Obviously, you include citations so that if someone's reading your paper and they want to know the details of your methods, they look up your citation.
Nobody reading that paper is thinking, oh, this is what Claudine Gay had to say.
No, that's, again, not how it works.
So that leads to the, you know, what they think of as their trump card, which is the APA citation guidelines,
which clearly say you have to put quoted text in quotes.
And that is true.
It's true now.
It was not true in 1987.
You see, 1987, the internet was just getting started, meaning this kind of plagiarism that, you know, academics and all teachers really have to deal with today.
It wasn't as big of a thing back then.
The APA citation guidelines were developed as kind of a result of the ubiquity of the internet.
Lots more opportunities to plagiarize.
So my question to Chris Ruffo is, could you please show me the citation guidelines that were applicable at Harvard in the political science department in 1997,
because those are the citation guidelines that Claudine Gay was supposed to follow and show me where in those guidelines, where did Claudine Gay not follow those guidelines?
Obviously, like, I'm not going to get an answer, right?
Like I said, the entire thing is bullshit.
But, and this may or may not surprise you, that hasn't stopped a huge number of people from taking Chris Ruffo's claims at face value.
They just assume Claudine Gay must have plagiarized her thesis.
You got these two pieces of text and they look pretty similar.
And they're waving the APA citation guidelines from 20 years after the fact in your face.
And it can look like a convincing case.
Until you poke at it a bit and it all falls apart.
But nobody bothers to poke at it.
Can you guess why?
A lot of the people who are kind of assuming this is true, they have internalized biases about, well, particularly black folks that kind of make them think,
oh, well, I guess that's not very surprising.
I mean, she is a black woman, president of Harvard.
Must have gotten there due to the color of her skin.
You know, it's not like she could have come by a PhD, honestly.
And, you know, to be frank, the color of Claudine Gay's skin is important to her being Harvard president.
Harvard's been around for, what, 500 years and she's the first black president?
Like, that's valuable to Harvard.
And this, like, she's only published 12 papers?
College presidents don't publish papers.
They're administrators.
So, yeah, like, this whole op just really annoys me.
Because it's so stupid.
But what really bothers me is how many people are just sort of like, oh, well, that makes sense.
And not realizing that they just got played by Chris Ruffo and their own internalized bias.
And, uh, I guess, to the end for this time.